{"tossups": [{"question": "During a conflict in this region, the Grey Wolves deployed one thousand militia under the guidance of Isgandar Hamidov. Mediation by Medetkhan Sheremkulov [[meh-det-KAHN sheh-rem-KOO-lof]] successfully ended the first conflict named for this region with the Bishkek Protocol. This region's <em>de facto</em> capital, Stepanakert [[step-AH-nah-kehrt]], experienced ethnic cleansing of its Muslim minority, leading to intervention by the government in Baku. Armenia and Azerbaijan fought multiple wars over, for ten points, what region in the South Caucasus, provisionally controlled by the Republic of Artsakh?", "answer": "<b><u>Nagorno-Karabakh</u></b> (accept Republic of <b><u>Artsakh</u></b> before mentioned; accept <b><u>Nagorno-Karabakh</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was killed in action after spearheading an attack on a blockhouse during which he rallied troops with the cry \u201cCome on, my good soldiers, your General calls upon you.\u201d With the help of David Wooster, this man besieged Fort St. John, which was then under the command of Guy Carleton. A poem notes how this man died on a battlefield \u201cting'd with blood that gush'd from Moncalm's veins\u201d during a campaign in which his forces were joined with those of Benedict Arnold. For ten points, name this Continental Army general who led the 1775 invasion of Quebec.", "answer": "Richard <b><u>Montgomery</u></b> (accept \"Elegy on the death of Gen. <b><u>Montgomery</u></b>\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An inscription found at Sant' Agata dei Goti suggests that this man built a temple to Serapis on the Quirinal Hill. The <em>dediticii</em> [[ded-ee-tee-KEE-ee]] who surrendered in combat were an exception to this man\u2019s edict greatly extending Roman citizenship. A set of <em>palaestras</em> were found in a building named for this man containing a <em>frigidarium</em>. Following the Praetorian Guard\u2019s assassination of his brother, Geta, this man became the sole ruler of Rome before himself being killed in 219. For ten points, name this eldest son of Septimius Severus and namesake of a large complex of Roman baths.", "answer": "<b><u>Caracalla</u></b> (or Marcus Aurelius Antoninus \"<b><u>Caracalla</u></b>\"; accept Baths of <b><u>Caracalla</u></b>; or Terme di <b><u>Caracalla</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "On March 17, 1992, the Israeli embassy in this country was bombed by the Islamic Jihad Organization. That bombing occurred two years prior to a bombing in this country's capital of a Jewish Community Center called AMIA. This country's president, Carlos Saul Menem, ordered the release of files relating to this country's role in protecting Nazi war criminals, including Adolf Eichmann. For ten points, name this South American country, where Jewish journalist Jacobo Timerman wrote about the Dirty War.", "answer": "<b><u>Argentina</u></b> (accept <b><u>Argentine</u></b> Republic; accept Republica <b><u>Argentina</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A conflict over the imperial succession in this period gave rise to the Hogen Rebellion. Retired emperors withdrew to monasteries but still held influence over government during this period's \"Cloistered Rule, and beginning in this period, noble women began wearing a particular twelve-layered robe. The Fujiwara clan dominated politics during this period, in which a work known as <em>The Pillow Book</em> was written. The Taira [[tah-EE-rah]] clan was defeated at the end of this period during the Genpei War. For ten points, name this period of cultural flourishing in classical Japan.", "answer": "<b><u>Heian</u></b> Period (accept <b><u>Heian</u></b> jidai; prompt on \"Twelfth Century\" or \"1100s\" before \"robe\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1977, one of these places was created after Steve Rubell and Ian Schrager converted a theatre. In 1986, one of these places in West Germany, known as <em>La Belle</em>, was bombed, prompting Ronald Reagan to order Operation El Dorado Canyon against Libya. Studio 54 was a prominent example of these locations, another of which was the site of Omar Mateen\u2019s mass shooting in Florida. For ten points, name these locations which include Pulse in Orlando.", "answer": "<b><u>Nightclub</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Music Club</u></b>; accept <b><u>Disco</u></b>theque; accept <b><u>Disco</u></b> Club; accept <b><u>Dance Club</u></b>; accept <b><u>Gay Bar</u></b>s; prompt on \"Club\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "An attempt to establish quotas to raise 140,000 troops in this country was part of a policy called the Union of Arms. The county of Rousillon [[roo-see-YOHN]] was in the Northeastern March of this country in the late-15th century. Italian Ambrogio Spinola conquered Breda while leading the army of this country, whose forces were devastated by the French at Rocroi [[roh-KWAH]], ending the dominance of this country's Tercios. For ten points, name this Great Power of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, once ruled by Philip II.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Spain</u></b> (accept Reino de <b><u>Espa\u00f1a</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Though not by Karl Marx, this work claims that humanity \u201cdoes not passively submit to the presence of nature\u201d in its section \u201cThe Point of View of Historical Materialism.\" Three years prior to this work, its author eschewed an ethical framework in a book titled <em>The</em> <em>Ethics of Ambiguity</em>. Divisions between \u201cthe subject\u201d and \u201cthe Other\u201d are drawn in this work, which argues that \u201cone is not born but becomes\u201d a member of the title group. Written by the lover of Jean-Paul Sartre, for ten points, what is this feminist book by Simone de Beauvoir [[boh-VWAH]]?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Second Sex</u></b></em> (accept <em>Le</em> <em><b><u>Deuxi\u00e8me Sexe</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This composer wrote the music for <em>The Plow That Broke the Plains</em> for the U.S. government's Resettlement Administration. This rival of Aaron Copland chronicled the life of Susan B. Anthony and the women's suffrage movement in his opera <em>The Mother of Us All</em>. This music critic for the <em>New York Herald Tribune</em> drew from the lives of Ignatius of Loyola and Teresa of Avila for an operatic collaboration with Gertrude Stein. For ten points, name this American composer who wrote <em>Four Saints in Three Acts</em>.", "answer": "Virgil <b><u>Thomson</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "After this occurrence, the central figure\u2019s bodyguards, known as the \u201cskullcrushers,\u201d assassinated this event's perpetrator. Rexford Tugwell claimed that this event resulted in \u201ca beneficent peace [throughout] the land.\u201d The defeat of Benjamin Pavy may have contributed to this event, which was carried out by a physician from Baton Rouge named Carl Weiss. This event brought about the end of the Share Our Wealth program, led by its central Louisiana politician. For ten points, name this event in which a populist governor nicknamed \u201cThe Kingfish\u201d was killed.", "answer": "<b><u>Assassination</u></b> of Huey (Pierce) <b><u>Long</u></b> Jr. (prompt on \u201cassassination of the Kingfish\u201d before mentioned; prompt on partial answers; accept equivalents in place of \"assassination\" such as \u201ckilling\u201d or \u201cmurder\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One soldier in this battle, William Hoffman, wrote a diary of his experiences which was chronicled through the eyes of a doctor in a work by Heinz Konsalik. Anthony Beevor won a Wolfson Prize for a book about this battle, which was the subject of a Heinrich Gerlach novel about a <em>Breakout at</em> [its central location]. A work about the <em>Survivors of</em> [this battle] includes a number of \u201cEyewitness Accounts from the Sixth Army.\u201d For ten points, name this World War Two battle on the Eastern Front with more than 1.1 million Soviet casualties alone.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Stalingrad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "An object set in place by this act was preceded by an object depicting the \u201cFugio.\" This act created an institution whose officers included an engraver, and this act authorized the creation of a building whose cornerstone was laid by David Rittenhouse. Harsh penalties against \u201cdebasement\u201d were listed in this act, which authorized half and quarter eagles and called for an inscription of \u201cUnited States of America\u201d on certain gold and silver objects.  Creating the U.S. Mint, for ten points, what was this act that dealt with hard currency?", "answer": "<b><u>Coinage</u></b> Act of 1792 (accept <b><u>Mint</u></b> Act before \"Mint\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man once said, \u201cMan will never be free until the last king is strangled with the entrails of the last priest.\u201d This man's financial troubles were relieved when he was hired as the personal librarian to Catherine the Great. A three-part piece describing the structure of this man\u2019s best-known work took the form of a \u201cPreliminary Discourse\u201d authored by Jean d\u2019Alembert [[dah-lem-BEHR]]. That Enlightenment-era work assembled by this man included a number of supplements and extra volumes. For ten points, name this founder of the <em>Encyclop\u00e9die</em>.", "answer": "Denis <b><u>Diderot</u></b> [[dee-deh-ROH]]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "After the 1977 elections in this country, the UTHR-J organization accused the United National Party of orchestrating pogroms against this nation's second largest ethnic group. A 1983 pogrom in this country, called Black July, helped spark the first phase of this country's Eelam War One. This country became a republic and received its current name under the premiership of Sirimavo Bandaranaike [[bahn-dar-ah-NYE-keh]] in 1972. For ten points, name this South Asian country where a 25-year civil war ended in 2009 after this country's predominantly Sinhalese government defeated the Tamil Tigers.", "answer": "Democratic Socialist Republic of <b><u>Sri Lanka</u></b> (or <b><u>Ila\u1e45kai</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Ceylon\" since all clues are post-1972)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "At least 4,000 prisoners were once sacrificed by this empire at a yearly event known as its namesake \u201cAnnual Customs.\u201d Francisco F\u00e9lix de Sousa was a <em>chacha</em> of Ouidah who helped a leader of this empire ascend to power. A military unit consisting entirely of women was known as the namesake Amazons of this empire, once led by Ghezo. The Fon people made up this empire, which declined following the abolition of the slave trade. For ten points, name this African empire based in modern-day Benin.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Dahomey</u></b> (or <b><u>Dahomey</u></b> Empire; accept Annual Customs of <b><u>Dahomey</u></b>; accept <b><u>Dahomey</u></b> Amazons)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In describing this conflict, Major Meredith compared the targeted group to Zulu warriors in that both demonstrated heavy resistance even after being shot. George Pearce was called the \u201cMinister of [this conflict],\" during which Lewis Guns were employed against a group in the Campion district. The failure of attempts to herd the central group, whose migration led to widespread destruction of crops, contributed to this event. Targeting a species of flightless animals, for ten points, what was this \u201cwar\u201d against an Australian bird?", "answer": "Great <b><u>Emu</u></b> War (accept Minister of the <b><u>Emu</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In an article titled \u201cThe Russian Menace,\u201d this person argued that the U.S. military posed a threat to Russian citizens. Ian McLellan Hunter received writing credit on behalf of this person for <em>Roman Holiday</em>. A statue installed at Grand Junction depicts this person writing in a bathtub. This scriptwriter of <em>Spartacus</em> was blacklisted after refusing to testify before the House Un-American Activities Committee. For ten points, what screenwriter was a part of the Hollywood Ten and inspired a film starring Bryan Cranston?", "answer": "Dalton <b><u>Trumbo</u></b> (or James Dalton <b><u>Trumbo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Glenn Greenwald wrote an article criticizing this organization\u2019s decision to forgo the word \u201ctorture\u201d when describing tactics used by the Bush administration toward terrorism suspects. In 2017, tweets by this organization quoting the Declaration of Independence were labeled by critics as \u201cpropaganda\u201d against Donald Trump. The first broadcast of this organization was coverage of the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations hearings on the Vietnam War on April 20, 1971. For ten points, what American news broadcaster operates as a non-profit media network?", "answer": "<b><u>NPR</u></b> (or <b><u>N</u></b>ational <b><u>P</u></b>ublic <b><u>R</u></b>adio)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A 2002 case between this company and <em>Step Two</em> centered on internet personal jurisdiction. After returning from World War Two, Charles Lazarus founded this company after a stint selling cradles from his father\u2019s bicycle shop. In 2017, this company filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy after having lost much of its market share to online retailers. Tru Kids owns the brand for this company, whose iconic \u201cspokes-animal\u201d mascot was Geoffrey the Giraffe. For ten points, name this retailer of children\u2019s products that closed all of its U.S. locations in 2021.", "answer": "<b><u>Toys \u201cR\u201d Us</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of this organization once allegedly said, \u201cWe are not at war with the</u></b> <b><u>administration\u2026just do the work.\u201d One CEO of this organization, who has chaired the</u></b> <b><u>Ronald Reagan Presidential Foundation, is Fred Ryan. (+)</u> During an interview with David Rubenstein, a leader of this organization spoke of the importance of scrutinizing public figures. After his work at </b><em><b>The Boston Globe</b></em><b>, Marty Baron became editor of this publication, which was purchased for $250 million by Jeff (*) </b>Bezos of Amazon. For ten points, name this daily newspaper serving the D.C. metropolitan area.", "answer": "<em>The Washington</em> <em><b><u>Post</u></b></em> (accept \"<b><u>WaPo</u></b>\"; prompt on the \"Post\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>American physician Samuel Gridley Howe wrote a \"Historical Sketch\" named</u></b> <b><u>for this conflict while serving as a surgeon. Prior to this war, the fraternal</u></b> <b><u>brotherhood Filiki Eteria attempted to recruit future president, and Tsar Alexander's</u></b> <b><u>foreign minister, John Capodistrias (+)</u> to lead this revolt. Eug\u00e8ne Delacroix [[deh-lah-KWAH]] immortalized a tragedy during this war in his painting (*) </b><em>Massacre at Chios</em> [[KYE-ohss]], and Lord Byron died from fever outside Lepanto during this war. For ten points, name this 1821 anti-Ottoman revolt which included the Battle of Navarino and the Siege of the Acropolis.", "answer": "<b><u>Greek Independence</u></b> War (or <b><u>Greek</u></b> War of <b><u>Independence</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Greek</u></b> <b><u>Revolution</u></b> of 1821; accept <b><u>Elliniki Epanastasi</u></b>; accept <b><u>Agonas</u></b> but prompt on \"Struggle\"; accept <b><u>Yunan \u0130syan\u0131</u></b> but prompt on \"Greek Rebellion\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Historian William of Newburgh stated that this work would be believed by</u></b> <b><u>someone \"ignorant of ancient history\" and wrote that the author \"lied about</u></b> <b><u>everything.\" This work was directly inspired by the Venerable Bede's</u> </b><em><b><u>Ecclesiastical</u></b></em> <em><b><u>History</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> This book ends with the Battle of Camlann, where both Mordred and his father fall in battle, resulting in the rise of the (*) </b>Anglo-Saxon kings. Geoffrey of Monmouth wrote a pseudohistorical account in, for ten points, what 12th century book that popularized the legend of Arthur?", "answer": "<em>Historia</em> <em><b><u>Regum Britanniae</u></b></em> (accept <em>The History of the</em> <em><b><u>Kings of Britain</u></b></em>; accept <em>De</em> <em><b><u>gestis Britonum</u></b></em>; accept <em>On the</em> <em><b><u>Deeds of Britons</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this process, one man was presented with a silk screen landscape of</u></b> <b><u>the Huangshan Mountains, whereas the only thing that man had to offer in turn was a</u></b> <b><u>comb. This process was partly caused by Glenn Cowan missing his (+)</u> team's bus in Nagoya, after which he enjoyed a fifteen-minute conversation with three-time world champion Zhuang Zedong. Paving the way for (*) </b>Nixon's visit to a certain country, for ten points, what was this early 1970s series of events between players of a \"racquet\" sport that eased diplomatic tensions between the U.S. and China?", "answer": "<b><u>Ping-Pong Diplomacy</u></b> (<b><u>P\u012bngp\u0101ng w\u00e0iji\u0101o</u></b>; prompt on \u201cping pong\" or \u201ctable tennis\u201d; prompt on \u201ctable tennis diplomacy\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>The First Lateran Council, convened by Pope Callixtus II, reaffirmed an</u></b> <b><u>agreement in this city which included the emperor giving up his right to present</u></b> <b><u>ecclesiastics with a crosier. That \"Concordat\" in this European city, initially convened</u></b> <b><u>by (+)</u> Holy Roman Emperor Henry V, ended the 12th century Investiture Controversy. A 1521 assembly in this city, convened by Charles V, followed the papal bull </b><em><b>Exsurge Domine</b></em><b>, which aimed to refute some articles of the </b><em><b>Ninety-five Theses</b></em><b>. (*) </b>Martin Luther was declared a heretic during a diet [[DEE-et]] in, for ten points, which Rhenish city?", "answer": "<b><u>Worms</u></b> [[VURMS]] (accept Diet of <b><u>Worms</u></b>; accept Concordat of <b><u>Worms</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Jesus was once labelled the \"Crucified\" member of this philosophical tradition</u></b> <b><u>by Lucian in his work</u> </b><em><b><u>Peregrinus</u></b></em><b><u>. While in a debate with Pericles, one member of this</u></b> <b><u>philosophical school asked, \"Who is to blame if an athlete is killed by javelin?\" (+)</u></b> <b>wondering if one \"blames the javelin, the thrower, or the host of the games.\" A dialogue supposedly exposing this tradition's flaws, </b><em><b>Gorgias</b></em><b>, is named for an early figure in this movement known as \"The Nihilist.\" Protagoras [[proh-tah-GOH-rahs]] was (*) </b>an early figure in, for ten points, which Pre-Socratic school whom Plato depicted as charlatans?", "answer": "<b><u>Sophist</u></b>s (or <b><u>Sophist</u></b>ic; prompt on \"Nihilism\" before \"Nihilist\"; accept the Second <b><u>Sophist</u></b>s; accept Crucified <b><u>Sophist</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>Concerning his plans to create this opera, the composer once asked, \u201cWho</u></b> <b><u>doesn\u2019t know about the story of Zeus and Semele\u201d? A silent role was given to Gottfried</u></b> <b><u>in this opera, which features the Ottonian king, Henry the Fowler. Based on a</u></b> <b><u>character appearing in a work by Wolfram von (+)</u> Eschenbach [[EH-shehn-bahk]], this work\u2019s central character arrives aboard a boat headed by a swan to guard a noblewoman named Elsa. Many weddings (*) </b>feature the bridal chorus of this opera whose main character is the son of Parzival. For ten points, name this opera by Richard Wagner about a knight of the Holy Grail.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Lohengrin</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b><u>As a youth, one man told this figure that he would be \u201ca capable minister in</u></b> <b><u>peaceful times and an unscrupulous hero in chaotic times.\" In one portrayal, this man</u></b> <b><u>presented the Seven (+)</u> Gems Sword as a gift to another after a failed assassination attempt. This man lost what may have been the largest naval battle in history, after which he fled along the Dongting Lake. A lack of support among the populace of Jing province contributed to this man\u2019s defeat at Red (*) </b>Cliffs against the army of Liu Bei.  The state of Wei was led by, for ten points, what warlord of the Three Kingdoms era?", "answer": "<b><u>Cao Cao</u></b> [[ts'ow ts'ow]] (generously accept differing pronunciations like [[KOW KOW]]; accept <b><u>Mengde</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This politician once quipped that he would never get ulcers, because he says</u></b> <b><u>exactly what he thinks. Benjamin Ward was appointed as police commissioner by this</u></b> <b><u>man whose tenure included the Howard Beach incident. Al Sharpton (+)</u> organized protest marches in response to the death of the sixteen-year-old Yusef Hawkins during this man\u2019s mayoral administration. The 100th anniversary of the Brooklyn Bridge\u2019s 1889 completion was celebrated under this predecessor of (*) </b>David Dinkins.  For ten points, name this Jewish-American mayor of New York City from 1978 to 1989.", "answer": "Ed <b><u>Koch</u></b> (accept Edward Irving <b><u>Koch</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man legendarily was forced into exile to the Mema Kingdom with his</u></b> <b><u>sisters and mother due to a jealous wife of his polygamous father, Sassouma (+)</u></b> <b>Beret\u00e9 [[sah-SOO-mah beh-reh-TEH]]. This ruler's defeat of the sorcerer-king and Sosso leader Soumaoro Kant\u00e9 was recounted by oral poets known as </b><em><b>djeli</b></em><b> [[JEH-lee]] in the </b><em><b>Epic of</b></em><b> this monarch. The founder of the (*) </b>Keita Dynasty was, for ten points, which <em>mansa</em> and leader of the Mandinke, the great-uncle of Mansa Musa?", "answer": "<b><u>Sundiata</u></b> Kieta (accept <b><u>Manding Diara</u></b>; or <b><u>Sogolon Djata</u></b>; or <b><u>Nare Maghan</u></b>; or <b><u>Sogo Sogo Simbon Salaba</u></b>; prompt on \"Lion of Mali\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Members of the Marxist student organization</u> </b><em><b><u>Zengakuren</u></b></em><b><u> interrupted a</u></b> <b><u>speech by this man while on a visit to Japn, with this politician inviting the student up</u></b> <b><u>to the stage for an impromptu debate. From Jameson Hall, this (+)</u> American politician gave the \"Day of Affirmation\" speech likening the youth struggle of Apartheid to the that of African-Americans in the American South. Motivated by Pro-Palestinian sentiment, Sirhan Sirhan gunned down this political figure outside the Ambassador (*) </b>Hotel. For ten points, name this Irish-American Attorney General and sibling of President John F.", "answer": "<b><u>R</u></b>obert F. <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> (or <b><u>RFK</u></b>; accept <b><u>Bob</u></b>by <b><u>Kennedy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In this nation, Italian missionary Giuseppe Berton's \"Family Homes</u></b> <b><u>Movement\" protected over 3,000 child soldiers during an eleven year struggle. Along</u></b> <b><u>with native forces, a \"Special Task Force\" sent by Liberian president Charles (+)</u></b> <b>Taylor assisted in committing the atrocity \"Operation No Living Thing\" in this state. It's not Guinea-Bissau, but the mutual assistance organization ECOMOG, led by Nigeria, invaded this nation in an effort to defeat the Revolutionary United Front. Forces opposed to Joseph (*) </b>Momoh seized control of, for ten points, what war-torn West African nation whose civil strife was partially funded by the sale of \"blood diamonds?\"", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Sierra Leone</u></b> (accept <b><u>Salone</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}